This is a representation of your brain,
هذه الصورة تمثل الدماغ
and your brain can be broken into two parts.
ان الدماغ مقسوم الى قسمين
There's the left half, which is the logical side,
القسم الايسر هو القسم المنطقي
and then the right half,
والقسم الايمن
which is the intuitive.
هو القسم البديهي
And so if we had a scale to measure the aptitude of each hemisphere,
وان استطعنا ان نقيس " تجاوب " القسمين
then we can plot our brain.
يمكننا ان نصنف نوع الدماغ
And for example, this would be somebody who's completely logical.
فهذا على سبيل المثال دماغ شخص منطقي تماماً
This would be someone who's entirely intuitive.
وهذا دماغ شخص بديهي تماماً
So where would you put your brain on this scale?
برأيك ما هو تقييم دماغك ؟
Some of us may have opted for one of these extremes,
صحيح ان البعض يكون أحادي الدماغ
but I think for most people in the audience,
ولكن معظم الاشخاص .. بمن فيهم الحضور
your brain is something like this --
يملكون دماغاً كهذا ..
with a high aptitude in both hemispheres at the same time.
لديه فعالية في كلا القسمين في ذات الوقت
It's not like they're mutually exclusive or anything.
فالامر ليس ان تكون اما منطقياً .. او بديهياً
You can be logical and intuitive.
فانت يمكن ان تكون الاثنين
And so I consider myself one of these people,
وانا اعتبر نفسي من هذه الفئة
along with most of the other experimental quantum physicists,
فانا و " فيزائي الكم التجريبيين "
who need a good deal of logic
نحتاج كماً جيداً من المنطق
to string together these complex ideas.
لكي نستطيع ان نجول بين الافكار المعقدة
But at the same time, we need a good deal of intuition
ولكن في ذات الوقت فنحن نحتاج كماً جيداً من البداهة
to actually make the experiments work.
لكي ننجح في تجاربنا
How do we develop this intuition? Well we like to play with stuff.
وكيف يمكن ان نطور البداهة ؟؟ حسناً يتم ذلك عن طريق " اللهو " بالاشياء والمعادلات والافكار
So we go out and play with it, and then we see how it acts,
لذا نحن نخرج خارج نطاق العمل .. ونلعب بالاشياء .. وندقق كيف تتجاوب مع ذلك
and then we develop our intuition from there.
ومن ثم نطور بداهتنا على هذا النحو
And really you do the same thing.
وانتم تقومون بنفس الامر ايضا
So some intuition
من بعض الامور البديهية
that you may have developed over the years
التي نعلمها جميعاً على مدى سنوات
is that one thing is only in one place at a time.
هي ان الشيء لا يتواجد الا في مكان واحد في لحظة زمنية ما
I mean, it can sound weird to think about
اعني انه من الغرابة ان نتخيل
one thing being in two different places at the same time,
فكرة ان يتواجد امرين في مكانين بذات الوقت
but you weren't born with this notion, you developed it.
ولكننا لم نولد بهذه " البديهية " نحن تعلمناها
And I remember watching a kid playing on a car stop.
اذكر اني شاهدت طفلاً يلعب في مصف سيارات ..
He was just a toddler and he wasn't very good at it, and he kept falling over.
كان يحاول ان يتجاوز عتبة المصف .. ولكنه كان يقع على الداوم
But I bet playing with this car stop taught him a really valuable lesson,
ولكن هذا الموقف علمه درساً اساسياً
and that's that large things don't let you get right past them,
هو ان الاشياء الكبيرة لا تسمح لك بالمرور عبرها
and that they stay in one place.
وتستقر في مكانها
And so this is a great conceptual model to have of the world,
وهذا مفهوم رائع للحياة
unless you're a particle physicist.
إلا اذا كنت فيزيائي جزيئات
It'd be a terrible model for a particle physicist,
فان ذلك لا ينطبق على فيزيائي الجزئيات
because they don't play with car stops,
لانهم لا يلعبون في مواقف السيارات
they play with these little weird particles.
انما يلعبون بالجزئيات الصغيرة الغريبة
And when they play with their particles,
وعندما يلعبون بتلك الجزئيات
they find they do all sorts of really weird things --
يجدون الكثير من الاشياء الغريبة
like they can fly right through walls,
مثل ايجاد القدرة على الطيران واختراق الجدران
or they can be in two different places at the same time.
او ان يتواجدوا في مكانين في نفس اللحظة الزمنية
And so they wrote down all these observations,
وقد كتبوا كل تلك الملاحظات الناتجة عن مراقبة الجزئيات
and they called it the theory of quantum mechanics.
واطلقوا على ذلك مسمى " نظرية ميكانيكا الكم "
And so that's where physics was at a few years ago;
وهكذا غدت الامور منذ بضع سنوات
you needed quantum mechanics
اصبحت تحتاج ميكانيكا الكم
to describe little, tiny particles.
لكي تصف الجزئيات الصغيرة
But you didn't need it
ولكنك لا تحتاجها لكي تصف
to describe the large, everyday objects around us.
الاجسام الكبير .. والاشياء التي تحيط بنا
This didn't really sit well with my intuition,
ولكن هذه المعلومات لم تتوافق مع " بديهتي "
and maybe it's just because I don't play with particles very often.
وربما حدث ذلك لانني لا ألعب عادة بالجزئيات الصغيرة
Well, I play with them sometimes,
انا ألعب بهم احيانا ..
but not very often.
ولكن ليس عادة
And I've never seen them.
انا لم آراهم
I mean, nobody's ever seen a particle.
أعني لم يرى أحدهم الجزئيات الصغيرة من قبل
But it didn't sit well with my logical side either.
ولكن ذلك أيضاً لم يتوافق مع " منطقيتي "
Because if everything is made up of little particles
لانه إن كان كل شيء مصنوع من الجزئيات الصغيرة
and all the little particles
وكل الجزئيات الصغيرة
follow quantum mechanics,
تتبع لميكانيكا الكم
then shouldn't everything just follow quantum mechanics?
إذاً الا يجب ان تنطبق ميكانيكا الكم على كل شيء ؟
I don't see any reason why it shouldn't.
انا لا ارى سبب يمنع هذا
And so I'd feel a lot better about the whole thing
لذا أردت أن أعيد النظر في الامر كله
if we could somehow show
وان احاول ان ابرهن بصورة ما
that an everyday object
ان كل شيء من حولنا
also follows quantum mechanics.
يتبع أيضاً ميكانيكا الكم
So a few years ago, I set off to do just that.
لذا من سنوات عدة بدأت بهذا المشروع
So I made one.
لقد صنعت
This is the first object
اول مجسم
that you can see
يمكنك ان ترى فيه نظرية ميكانيكا الكم
that has been in a mechanical quantum superposition.
والتموضع بحسبها
So what we're looking at here
ان ما تنظرون اليه
is a tiny computer chip.
هو رقاقة حاسوب صغيرة
And you can sort of see this green dot right in the middle.
يمكنكم ان تروا النقطة الخضراء في المنتصف
And that's this piece of metal I'm going to be talking about in a minute.
وهذه هي قطعة معدنية سأحدثكم عنها خلال دقائق
This is a photograph of the object.
هذه هي صورة للمجسم
And here I'll zoom in a little bit. We're looking right there in the center.
سوف اقرب لكم الصورة قليلاً .. انتم تنظرون الى المنتصف تحديداً
And then here's a really, really big close-up of the little piece of metal.
وهذه صورة مقربة جداً لقطعة المعدن تلك
So what we're looking at is a little chunk of metal,
وما تنظرون اليه هو قطعة معدنية
and it's shaped like a diving board, and it's sticking out over a ledge.
انها مُشكّلة كما عنفة الغوص وهي موضوعة على الحافة
And so I made this thing
لقد صنعت هذا الجهاز
in nearly the same way as you make a computer chip.
بصورة تشابه طريقة صناعة رقائق الكمبيوتر
I went into a clean room with a fresh silicon wafer,
فاستخدمت الغرف النظيفة .. ورقاقة سيلكون جديدة
and then I just cranked away at all the big machines for about 100 hours.
ومن ثم ادخلتها في هذه الاجهزة الكبيرة لمدة 100 ساعة
For the last stuff, I had to build my own machine --
ومن اجل مخططي كان يجب ان أبنى آلتي الخاصة
to make this swimming pool-shaped hole
لكي اصنع ما يشابه حوض سباحة
underneath the device.
اسفل الجهاز
This device has the ability
ان هذا الجهاز لديه القدرة
to be in a quantum superposition,
على ان يمثل " التموضع الكمي "
but it needs a little help to do it.
ولكنه يحتاج مساعدة للقيام بذلك
Here, let me give you an analogy.
دعوني اوضح ذلك
You know how uncomfortable it is to be in a crowded elevator?
هل تعلمون كم هو مزعج الشعور عندما تركبون مصعد مزدحم
I mean, when I'm in an elevator all alone, I do all sorts of weird things,
اعني .. عن نفسي .. عندما اركب مصعد وحدي .. فاني اقوم بأشياء " غريبة "
but then other people get on board
ولكن عندما يدخل اشخاص آخرين الى المصعد
and I stop doing those things
اتوقف عن تلك الاشياء
because I don't want to bother them,
لانني لا اريد ان ازعجهم
or, frankly, scare them.
او بتعبير آخر .. إخافتهم
So quantum mechanics says
ان ميكانيكا الكم تقول
that inanimate objects feel the same way.
ان العناصر الدقيقة المتناهية في الصغر تتصرف بنفس الشاكلة
The fellow passengers for inanimate objects
ان ما يحيط بالجزئيات
are not just people,
ليس أشخاصاً
but it's also the light shining on it
بل الانارة .
and the wind blowing past it and the heat of the room.
والهواء الذي يرتطم بها . والحرارة المحيطة
And so we knew, if we wanted to see
وكما نعلم ان اردنا
this piece of metal behave quantum mechanically,
ان نجعل قطعة المعدن
we're going to have to kick out all the other passengers.
لذا قررنا ان نبعد كل هؤلاء " الركاب "
And so that's what we did.
وهذا ما قمنا به
We turned off the lights,
ابعدنا الانارة ..
and then we put it in a vacuum and sucked out all the air,
وقمنا بسحب الهواء
and then we cooled it down
وتبريد الجهاز
to just a fraction of a degree above absolute zero.
الى درجة واحدة فوق الصفر المطلق
Now, all alone in the elevator,
والآن أصبح المجسم .. وحيداً في المصعد
the little chunk of metal is free to act however it wanted.
وهي حرة لكي تتصرف كما تريد
And so we measured its motion.
وكنا نريد ان نقيس حركتها .
We found it was moving in really weird ways.
ووجدنا انها تتحرك بصورة غريبة
Instead of just sitting perfectly still, it was vibrating,
بدلاً من ان تتوقف عن الحركة .. انها تهتز
and the way it was vibrating was breathing something like this --
وكانت تهتز كما لو انها تتنفس .. هكذا
like expanding and contracting bellows.
كما لو كانت وسادة مضغوطة تنتفخ تباعاً
And by giving it a gentle nudge,
وبهز الجهاز قليلاً
we were able to make it both vibrate
كنا على استطاعة بان نجعل الجسيم يهتز
and not vibrate
ولا يهتز
at the same time --
في وقت واحد !
something that's only allowed with quantum mechanics.
شيء يمكن القيام به فحسب في ميكانيكا الكم
So what I'm telling you here is something truly fantastic.
وانا اخبركم انه امرٌ رائع جداً
What does it mean for one thing
ولكن ماذا يعني
to be both vibrating and not vibrating
أن يهتز الجسيم .. ولا يهتز
at the same time?
في وقت واحد
So let's think about the atoms.
دعونا نذهب الى الذرات
So in one case:
من جهة ..
all the trillions of atoms that make up that chunk of metal
هناك ترليون ذرة قد شكلت الجسيم المعدني هذا
are sitting still
وهي ثابتة
and at the same time those same atoms
ولكن في نفس الوقت هذه الذرات
are moving up and down.
تتحرك الى الاعلى والاسفل
Now it's only at precise times when they align.
وفي اوقات متناهية في الصغر يتواكب الامرين
The rest of the time they're delocalized.
ولكن في باقي الوقت يحدث " عدم تموضع "
That means that every atom
وهذا يعني ان كل ذرة
is in two different places at the same time,
موجودة في مكانين مختلفين في وقت واحد
which in turn means the entire chunk of metal
وهذا يعني ان الجسيم المعدني
is in two different places.
موجود في مكانين في وقت واحد
I think this is really cool.
أليس هذا رائعاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Really.
حقاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It was worth locking myself in a clean room to do this for all those years
لقد كان الامر يستحق كل السنوات التي قضيتها في غرف التعقيم من اجل هذا
because, check this out,
لانه .. وتبعاً لهذا
the difference in scale
وعلى نطاق مختلف
between a single atom and that chunk of metal
من الذرة و الجسيم المعدني
is about the same as the difference
واختلافهم بين الحجم و الوزن
between that chunk of metal and you.
ان قطعة المعدن تلك تمثل نفس الشيء مقارنة بك
So if a single atom can be in two different places at the same time,
لذا ان كانت الذرة تستطيع ان تتواجد في مكانين في ذات الوقت
that chunk of metal can be in two different places,
والقطعة المعدنية تستطيع ان تتواجد في مكانين في ذات الوقت
then why not you?
إذا لم لا تستطيع أنت أيضاً ؟
I mean, this is just my logical side talking.
اعني أليس هذا منطقي !
So imagine if you're in multiple places at the same time,
تخيل ان تكون في مكانين في ذات الوقت
what would that be like?
كيف سيبدو ذلك لك ..
How would your consciousness
كيف سيتعامل عقلك الواعي
handle your body being delocalized in space?
مع " التموضع المختلف في الفضاء "
There's one more part to the story.
وهناك تكملة للقصة ..
It's when we warmed it up,
عندما قمنا برفع درجة الحرارة
and we turned on the lights and looked inside the box,
وبدانا باعادة الانوار الى داخل الصندوق
we saw that the piece metal was still there in one piece.
وجدنا ان القطعة المعدنية بقيت كما هي دون تغيير
And so I had to develop this new intuition,
ومن هنا كان علي ان أعي بديهية تنص على ان
that it seems like all the objects in the elevator
كل العناصر المحيطة في "المصعد "
are really just quantum objects
هي في الحقيقة عناصر تابعة ل " ميكانيكا الكم "
just crammed into a tiny space.
وقد حشرت في حيز ضيق جداً
You hear a lot of talk
الجميع يسمع الكثير من الافكار
about how quantum mechanics says that everything is all interconnected.
كيف ان ميكانيكا الكم تنص على ان شي " متكامل / مترابط " مع بعضه البعض
Well, that's not quite right.
ولكن الامر في الحقيقة ..
It's more than that; it's deeper.
اعمق من هذا بكثير ..
It's that those connections,
ان هذه الصلات ...
your connections to all the things around you,
صلاتك بالامور من حولك
literally define who you are,
هي في الحقيقة التي تحدد ماهيتك ( من أنت )
and that's the profound weirdness of quantum mechanics.
وهذا هو محور الغرابة في ميكانيكا الكم
Thank you.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)